Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ס''ד. Samech Daled.
We first wrap up the discussion of
the מצוה mitzvah of
לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi
or שוחט זבח—did shochet zevach I say that right?—לא תשחט על חמץ,
lo tishchat al chametz, yes, דם זבחי, dam zivchi, about שחיטה shechting
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach or the קרבנות Korbanot when one still
owns חמץ chametz and then we move on to a משנה Mishnah
that actually gets to the description of what it looked like when
they brought the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So we pick up here
on the bottom of ס''ג עמוד ב Samech Gimmel Amud Bet the
following.
ורמינהי, V'ramini, five lines from the bottom. This was after a statement
had just been made that not only is somebody חייב chayav for
doing שחיטה shechita and for doing זריקה, zerika, which isn't in the
פסוק—but pasuk זריקה zerika at least there's another פסוק pasuk that they
learn that out from—but even from doing the הקטרה haktara if somebody
owns חמץ chametz because the end of the פסוק pasuk is ולא
ילין חלב חגי עד בוקר v'lo yalin chelev chagi ad boker and
then the גמרא Gemara said well the כהן Kohen who does the
burning of the אימורים emurim is also in the category of לא
ילין lo yalin because he could leave over, be transgress הלנה halana
by leaving over the אימורים. emurim. So let's take a look on
this. ורמינהי, V'ramini, I'll ask on this, five lines from the bottom
on ס''ג עמוד ב. Samech Gimmel Amud Bet. השוחט את הפסח על
החמץ עובר בלא תעשה. Ha'shochet et ha'Pesach al ha'chametz over b'lo ta'aseh.
Somebody who שוחט shechts the פסח Pesach on חמץ, chametz, which means
somebody in the group, a related person, owns חמץ, chametz, the גמרא
Gemara before discussed whether it has to be present in the עזרה.
Azara. You transgress a negative prohibition. רבי יהודה אומר אף התמיד, Rabbi
Yehuda omer af ha'Tamid, even the תמיד, Tamid, even not only the
פסח Pesach on the 14th, even the תמיד. Tamid. אמרו לו לא
אמרו אלא בפסח בלבד, Amru lo, lo amru ela b'Pesach bilvad,
I'm sorry, to only by the פסח. Pesach. אימתי, Eimatai, when is
this true? בזמן שיש לו לשוחט או לזורק, Bizman sheyesh lo l'shochet
o l'zorek, if
who has to have חמץ chametz for it to be relevant? The
one doing the שחיטה shechita or the one doing the זריקה. zerika.
Presumably that's only relevant for if the person is doing, if the
זורק zorek is the one, if the זורק zorek owns חמץ chametz
for the זורק zorek to be over on, to be over on
it, but anyway, for the one doing the שחיטה, shechita, the one
doing the זריקה, zerika, או אחד מבני חבורה, o echad mivnei chaburah,
or one of the group. האי אחד בסוף העולם, Hai echad besof
ha'olam, if some stranger has it, אין זקוק לו, ein zakuk lo,
that's not your responsibility.
Okay, so who owns the חמץ? chametz? The שוחט, shochet, the זורק,
zorek, or one of the people of the חבורה. chaburah. ואחד השוחט
ואחד הזורק ואחד המליק ואחד המזה חייב. V'echad ha'shochet v'echad ha'zorek v'echad
ha'malik v'echad ha'mazeh chayav.
Now who transgresses? What act do you transgress for? Whether you do
the שחיטה shechita or the זריקה zerika or the מליקה melika or
whether you sprinkle the blood. Now מזה mazeh is similar to זורק
zorek in that מזה mazeh refers to the getting of the blood
on the מזבח mizbeach if you're doing מליקה, melika, if it's a
bird. So the last two המליק hamalik and מזה mazeh parallel שוחט
shochet and זורק. zorek. But what it says is you're חייב chayav
for here for מליקה. melika. אבל הקומץ את המנחה אינו עובר בלא
תעשה. Aval ha'kometz et ha'mincha eino over b'lo ta'aseh.
But the one who does, if it's a מנחה mincha and you
do קמיצה kmitza on the מנחה, mincha, which is somewhat parallel, right,
you have שחיטה shechita by animals, מליקה melika by birds, and קמיצה
kmitza by מנחה, mincha, but by מנחה mincha you're not, you don't
transgress because that's not at all similar, it's not about blood and
so on. מקטיר אימורים אינו עובר בלא תעשה. maktir emurim eino over
b'lo ta'aseh.
Similarly
the person who does the הקטרה haktara is not over on a
לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So this ברייתא Baraita first of all did
extend it to מליקה, melika, okay, but what it excluded was הקטרה.
haktara. Okay and that's sort of the reverse of what we said
yesterday. Yesterday we excluded מליקה melika but we included הקטרה. haktara. Right,
this includes מליקה melika and excludes הקטרה haktara and yesterday we did
the exact opposite. So the גמרא Gemara says that at the very
top here of ס''ד עמוד א, Samech Daled Amud Aleph, קשיא מליקה
אמליקה קשיא הקטרה אהקטרה. kashya melika a-melika kashya haktara a-haktara. Conflict, meaning
it's not self-contradictory but it contradicts the earlier ברייתא. Baraita. One ברייתא
Baraita says מליקה melika you're חייב chayav for, the other says no.
One says הקטרה haktara you're חייב chayav for, the other says no.
Okay and they reversed which one. So the גמרא Gemara says לטעמיך,
l'taimeich, wait a minute, according to your reasoning, meaning you're bothered by
the implications of this ברייתא, Baraita, תיקשי לך היא גופא, tikshi lach
hi gufa, the ברייתא—you Baraita should have asked a question, it's internally
contradictory. דתני, Ditani, the ברייתא Baraita starts by saying לא אמרו אלא
בפסח בלבד, lo amru ela b'Pesach bilvad, right, they rejected the idea
that it's talking about the תמיד, Tamid, that the prohibition includes the
תמיד. Tamid. They said no no no, the beginning of the ברייתא
Baraita said it does not include the תמיד, Tamid, it only is
about the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. והדר תני, V'hadar tani, and then
it says ואחד השוחט ואחד הזורק ואחד המליק ואחד המזה v'echad ha'shochet
v'echad ha'zorek v'echad ha'malik v'echad ha'mazeh and gives an example of מליקה.
melika. מליקה, melika, excuse me, does not happen by a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. So how is it that the beginning of the ברייתא
Baraita says this only applies to the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
the end of the ברייתא Baraita says, oh, you know who transgresses?
The guy who does מליקה melika on the birds. The guy who
does מליקה melika on the birds is not doing a קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. So how do you make sense of this ברייתא Baraita
anyway?
Yes, someone remind me, why are there birds on the 14th?
There's no reason. If somebody happens to bring a bird—now רש''י Rashi
says that it could be an example because birds are very common
in קרבנות Korbanot that are brought to end a טהרה tahara process
for מחוסרי כיפורים. mechusrei kippurim. So if somebody who let's say a
יולדת... yoledet... somebody who, let's say, a יולדת Yoledet or somebody who
needs this bird, a זבה, Zava, זב, Zav, right, and then they
need it to be brought so that then they can eat the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, which is why רש"י Rashi says we could
be talking about it being brought after the תמיד, Tamid, because that's
the only קרבן Korban other than the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach which
is allowed to be brought after a תמיד Tamid are those that
finish up the טהרה Tahara process.
But for whatever random reason there happens to be a bird sacrifice,
there's not an obligatory bird sacrifice, it says if you did the
מליקה Melika and you own חמץ, Chametz, or maybe the owners own
חמץ, Chametz, not exactly clear, anyway, you transgress. So the הגמרא Gemara
says, but you said you only transgress for the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. What's the story? קרבן פסח Korban Pesach only or even for
other things? So this is itself a problem. So the הגמרא Gemara
says, אלא הא
והא רבי שמעון. Ela ha veha Rabbi Shimon. They're both רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. Now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you'll remember says in our
משנה, Mishna, he said it's an interesting position. He says on the
14th only the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. No other קרבן, Korban, not
the תמיד, Tamid, nothing else. On the rest of יום טוב, Yom
Tov, from the 15th till the end, till the end of יום
טוב, Yom Tov, including חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, if you שחט shacht
any קרבן Korban and you own חמץ, Chametz, you transgress. So this
issue of are you חייב chayav for מליקה, Melika, do we or
is it only the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? The הגמרא Gemara says
there's an easy answer to it. אידי ואידי רבי שמעון. Idi ve-idi
Rabbi Shimon. They're both רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the משנה Mishna
who again says you could be חייב chayav during פסח Pesach for
other קרבנות. Korbanot. מליקה
מליקה לא קשיא. Melika Melika lo kashya. It's not a contradiction מליקה
Melika and מליקה. Melika.
כאן בארבעה עשר כאן בחולו של מועד. Kan bearba'ah asar kan becholo
shel moed. When did he say nothing other than the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, you're not even חייב chayav for the תמיד? Tamid? That
is on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. ערב פסח Erev Pesach you're only
חייב chayav for שחט-ing shacht the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. But on
the יום טוב Yom Tov itself, which by the way makes sense
because on the יום טוב Yom Tov itself that's really the חג
המצות, Chag HaMatzos, that's really when חמץ Chametz is אסור assur is
during those seven days. So during those seven days, then you're חייב
chayav on all קרבנות Korbanot including including מליקה. Melika. Okay, so that
deals with that problem.
And the only thing is, he is a one person who's talking,
makes two sentences, and doesn't tell you he's changing context from the
first sentence to the second. Not exactly עיקר חסר מן הספר, Ikar
chaser min hasefer, it's the עיקר Ikar was the this, but it's
the context that's חסר מן הספר. chaser min hasefer.
Right, but the point was a little, that is true that it's
funny when you do such a shift within the ברייתא Baraita without
saying the different contexts. But a way to understand it is, is
that the first discussion was focused on the question of what type
of קרבן Korban are you חייב chayav for on the 14th. And
the תנא Tanna says תמיד Tamid and it says no, you're not
חייב chayav for תמיד Tamid only פסח. Pesach. The next was a
more abstract discussion about what acts are you חייב chayav for. So
oh, the acts, you could be חייב chayav for מליקה. Melika. When,
okay, we're not discussing that, but the acts include the act of
מליקה. Melika. So it's not so bad. It's not like we're saying
in one sentence you're פטור patur for birds and the next sentence
then you're חייב chayav for birds. You know, so we're switching from
objects to acts.
Okay, so that's the resolution. So are you חייב chayav for מליקה
Melika or not? Well, מליקה Melika is as bad as שחיטה shechita
during
פסח Pesach itself, when all קרבנות Korbanot are אסור. assur. It includes
שחיטה, shechita, it includes מליקה, Melika, it just doesn't include מנחות. menachot.
Okay, but on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, that's a different story. ערב
פסח Erev Pesach it's just about the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And
then it's not just מליקה Melika that's excluded, it's all other קרבנות
Korbanot that are excluded. Okay, so that deals with the מליקה Melika
contradiction.
ואידי ואידי רבי שמעון היא, Ve'idi ve'idi Rabbi Shimon hee, and in
the other case both are also רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The הקטרה
Haktara contradiction. הקטרה הקטרה נמי לא קשיא. Haktara Haktara nami lo kashya.
There's not a contradiction about הקטרה. Haktara. Are you חייב chayav for
הקטרה Haktara or not? The first ברייתא Baraita said you were, the
second ברייתא Baraita said you were not. תנאי. Tannai. Well, it actually
is a contradiction, but okay, it's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. דאיכא
דמקיש הקטרה לשחיטה ואיכא דמאן דלא מקיש. De'ika demakish haktara leshechita ve'ika
deman dela makish.
This claim we made yesterday is not universal. The פסוק pasuk says
לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי ולא ילין חלב חגי עד בוקר.
Lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi velo yalin chelev chagi ad boker.
So it connects the שחיטה shechita with הלנה. hallanah. הלנה hallanah suggests
also the act of burning the fat. That's also a problem of
ילין חלב חגי. yalin chelev chagi. It doesn't only suggest, it speaks
about the fats. So the second part of the פסוק pasuk speaks
about הקטרה. haktara. So is the act of הקטרה haktara included in
the prohibition? That's a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. So it's a little
complicated, but what have we said? We basically have said the following.
What acts are you חייב chayav for? You're חייב chayav clearly in
the פסוק pasuk לא תשחט, lo tishchat, שחיטה. shechita. According to a
מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha interestingly not even quoted in the הגמרא, Gemara,
you're also חייב chayav for זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. How about for
burning the אימורין emurim if somebody owned חמץ? chametz? That's the end
of the פסוק, pasuk, ולא ילין חלב חגי עד בוקר, velo yalin
chelev chagi ad boker, speaks about the burning of the אימורין. emurim.
Would that also be included? That we have just said is a
debate, different versions of the ברייתא, Baraita, some say you're חייב chayav
for הקטרה, haktara, some say you're not. That's the act you're חייב
chayav for. Now, what type of an animal are you חייב chayav
for on ערב פסח? Erev Pesach? There are those that say the
תמיד. Tamid. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, only the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. On פסח Pesach itself, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says then
I'll be מחייב mechayev you for anything. That's really when the time
of פסח Pesach is, when the time
of פסח Pesach is. That's the type of קרבן korban *korban* you're
חייב chayav, *chayav* for. So we got the acts, right, שחיטה shchitah
*shechitah*, זריקה *zrikah*, maybe הקטרה *haktarah*. We've got the animals, ערב פסח
Erev Pesach *Erev Pesach* according to רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* just קרבן
פסח korban pesach *korban pesach*, on פסח pesach *Pesach* itself any animal
including birds but only animals. And then who owns חמץ chametz, *chametz*
is primarily the people of the בני החבורה *bnei hachaburah* but also
if you're the one doing the forbidden act like the שחיטה shchitah
*shechitah* or the זריקה *zrikah* then if you own חמץ chametz. *chametz*
it also but the only person that's חייב *chayav* is not the
owner of the חמץ *chametz* but the one who is doing the
act of הקרבה *hakravah*. All right, you're going to be tested on
all this tomorrow.
All right, the מנחה *minchah* is excluded because the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says על דם *al dam*,
דם *dam* and חלב *chelev*, right, so birds that at least have
דם *dam*. Exactly. Okay, now we continue. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yehuda omer, אף התמיד *Rabbi Yehuda omer af hatamid*. Now רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* does not include a wide range of קרבנות
korbanot *korbanot* but he does include the תמיד *tamid* on ערב פסח
Erev Pesach *Erev Pesach*. So מאי טעמא Mai Ta'ama? דרבי יהודה *mai
taama d'Rabbi Yehuda*? And רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* disagrees. What's the reason
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*? אמר לך *amar lach* זבחי
*zivchi*, it says מאי זבח *mai zevach*, זבח המיוחד לי *zevach hameyuchad
li*, so my regular sacrifice or the one unique to me, I'd
say regular maybe the point here, ומאן הוא תמיד *uman hu tamid*.
That is the תמיד *tamid*. So מאי זבחי *mai zivchi*, right, if
you ask what is the קרבן korban *korban* brought on the מזבח
mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*, it is the עולת תמיד העשויה בהר סיני *olat tamid
asuyah behar Sinai*, right, it's called the המזבח העולה *hamizbe'ach ha-olah* we're
going to say in a minute. So it is the תמיד *tamid*
and therefore it includes the תמיד *tamid* according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*.
מאי *mai* מן הקדוש ברוך הוא *m'Hakadosh Baruch Hu*?
רבי שמעון אומר הפסח בערב פסח Pesach *Rabbi Shimon omer hapesach b'erev
pesach*. Now רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says on ערב פסח Erev Pesach.
*Erev Pesach* only the פסח pesach. *Pesach* and on the חג *chag*
itself any קרבן korban *korban*. מאי טעמא Mai ta’ama? דרבי שמעון *mai
taama d'Rabbi Shimon*? What's the reason of רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*? דכתיב
*d'chativ* זבחי זבחי *zivchi zivchi* תרי זימני *trei zimnei*. That פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי *lo tishchat al chametz dam
zivchi* appears twice in the תורה Torah *Torah*. Appears once
in משפטים *Mishpatim* right after the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot* and then
after the whole חטא העגל *cheit ha'eigel* the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot*
given again and a little recap of משפטים *Mishpatim* happens again you
have the פסוק *pasuk* again. So it says that לא תשחט על
חמץ דם זבחי *lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi* twice. קרי ביה
*kari beih* so what you do is you take the יוד *yud*
from one of them and you take it off of one and
you put it on the other. It's like יהושע בן נון *Yehoshua
bin Nun*'s name. Okay so anyway קרי ביה *kari beih* זבח זבחי
*zevach zivchay*. By moving the יוד *yud* one becomes זבח *zevach* and
the other becomes זבחי *zivchay*. So זבח *zevach* is singular, one זבח
*zevach*, only the קרבן פסח korban pesach *korban pesach*. זבחי *zivchay* which
is what Michael was starting saying yesterday is my plural sacrifices which
is all קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot*. הלכתא *hilchata* ומאי הלכתא *v'mai hilchata* פלגינהו
רחמנא מהדדי *palginu rachmana mehadadi* ולא כתיב *v'lo ketiv* וכתב *v'katav* זבחי
*zivchay* so if the תורה Torah *Torah* really wanted to include other
קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* why didn't the תורה Torah *Torah* itself write it
that way זבחי *zivchay* why did it do זבחי זבחי *zivchi zivchi*
and we have to play around with moving a יוד *yud*? למימר
*l'meimar* to tell you בזמן דאיכא זבח *b'zman d'ika zevach* at a
time of זבח *zevach* לא מחייב אזיבחי *lo mechayev azivchay*. It's one
or the other. At the time when there's only one קרבן korban,
*korban* that matters in the world on ערב פסח pesach *Erev Pesach*,
the time of the זבח *zevach*, that's the only thing you're חייב
*chayav* for. בזמן דליכא זבח *b'zman d'leika zevach* at a time when
you don't have the זבח *zevach* מחייב אזיבחי *mechayev azivchay* that's when
you're חייב *chayav* on other קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. So each one has
their own area: ערב פסח pesach, *Erev Pesach* it's only for the
פסח pesach *Pesach*, on פסח pesach *Pesach* it's for all קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot*. Okay, I cannot help you here with how the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* does this דרשה *drasha*. Okay, and the last point, following רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* that you're חייב *chayav* on פסח pesach *Pesach* for
other קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* ובמועד לשמו פטור patur *u'b'moed lishmo patur*. On
the מועד moed. *moed* itself, meaning from the 15th through the end
of the חג *chag*, you are פטור *patur* if you shecht a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *korban pesach* לשמו *lishmo* קרבן פסח Korban Pesach.
*korban pesach*. Why are you פטור *patur*? Because if you shecht a
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *korban pesach* לשמו *lishmo* קרבן פסח korban pesach,
*korban pesach* on the 15th you made it into a no, if
you shecht it לשמו *lishmo* something else it's a זבח *zevach* לשמו
*lishmo* קרבן פסח korban pesach. *korban pesach* it's a פסח pesach *Pesach*
and a פסח pesach? *Pesach* שלא בזמנו *shelo b'zmano* was פסול pasul.
*pasul*. Okay, and רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* is of the position that
שחיטה shchitah שאינה ראויה לא שמה שחיטה shchitah? *shechitah she'einah reuyah lo
shemai shechitah* it doesn't even count as though you did an act
of שחיטה shechitah, *shechitah* and therefore you are exempt.
That same thing would be true if you shecht a second קרבן
פסח korban pesach, *korban pesach* on the 14th?
No, because that's an interesting question what would, well that would be
have to, it would be לשמו בעלים be'alim *lishmo ba'alim* but they
would not, well that's an interesting question, can you have that to
be,
probably it would be, I don't know if you could consider it
לשמו בעלים be'alim *lishmo ba'alim* once the בעלים be'alim. *ba'alim* are already
מנויים *minuyim* on their first קרבן פסח korban pesach? *korban pesach*. So
if they were to then go ahead and be מנוי *manui* on
a second קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. *korban pesach* they probably wouldn't be
considered שלא לשמו shelo lishmo בעלים *shelo lishmo ba'alim* and be פסול
pasul, *pasul* but I'd have to think about that. Okay, so but
presumably yes that would also be פסול pasul? *pasul*. Okay, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this טעמא דשלא לשמו *taama d'shelo lishmo*. The
reason that you're
פטור *patur* is you
shecht The reason you'd be חייב, we're going on the part that
you'd be חייב, is when you שחט shachted שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
and you made it into a שלמים shlamim during the during the
מועד. הא סתמא פטור. Ha stama patur. The suggestion is that if
you שחט shachted it with nothing in your head, you'd be פטור
because then it would סתם stam be a פסח pesach even though
it's already after the 14th, and it would be פסול. pasul? You
have to make it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo in order to to
turn it into a שלמים. shlamim. אמאי? Amai? Why do you have
to actively make it into a שלמים? shlamim? פסח בשאר ימות השנה
שלמים הוי. Pesach bishar yemot hashana shlamim havei. Even once it's the
rest of the year, certainly after it's after פסח pesach is over,
maybe on פורים Purim you might say that its default is פסח.
pesach But on the but after the 14th, it automatically is a
שלמים. shlamim.
It's funny you say חול המועד Chol HaMoed is שאר ימות השנה.
shar yemot hashana.
It is, relative to the 14th, right? So this is when it's
not the 14th and certainly after the 14th has passed, it's automatically
a שלמים. shlamim. Why do you have to consciously do it שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo to turn it into a שלמים? shlamim? שמע מינה,
Shma mina, should we infer from this פסח בשאר ימות השנה בעי
עקירה, pesach bishar yemot hashana ba'i akira, that a פסח pesach, in
the rest of the year, and again here the חידוש chiddush is
even after even after the 14th needs an active uprooting of its
status, that even after the 14th its default status is that of
a פסח, pesach. not of a שלמים. shlamim. And therefore if you
שחט shachted it סתם, stam, it would be פסול, pasul that you
need to actively do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo in order to
make it a שלמים. shlamim. אמר רבי חייא בר גמדא, Amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Gamda, נזרקה מפי חבורה, nizreka mipi chavura, it was thrown
out from the group, meaning like this was being discussed and everybody
came to a conclusion, the answer sort of emerged, ואמרו ve'amru and
they said, כגון שהיו בעלים טמאי מתים ונדחו לפסח שני דסתמיה לשם
פסח קאי. kegon shehayu be'alim t'mei meitim venidchu lepesach sheni destameih leshem
pesach ka'ei. No, no, no, it's a special case. Why didn't you
bring this פסח pesach. on the 14th? Because the owners were טמאי
מתים t'mei meitim and they couldn't bring it on the 14th. That's
not such a crazy scenario. Why wasn't it brought on the 14th?
Some reason they weren't able to bring it. But now the 15th
and חול המועד Chol HaMoed is not after its time. Why is
it not after its time? Because you'll hold it over and you'll
bring it a month from now. You can't bring it a year
from now, but you can bring it a month from now, you
can bring it for פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So in that case,
you need to actively change its name. But if it was a
if you had brought your קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. and the owners
brought a different קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. and this was leftover, then
this then this automatically becomes a שלמים. shlamim. But in this case,
it still retains its status of a פסח Pesach unless you actively
change the name. Yeah.
So between
14 ניסן Nisan and 14 אייר, Iyar, right, you have to actively
uproot it, but after 14 אייר Iyar it's kind of automatic?
After after the 14th of אייר, Iyar,
which is פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, after
after the 14th, yes, then it would automatically be considered a שלמים
shlamim without any... Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay. I just want to point
out that תוספות Tosafot reads the גמרא Gemara a little different because
תוספות Tosafot has the following question. תוספות Tosafot says, the גמרא's Gemara
question was the following. It says, not it's that why the גמרא
Gemara would even ask why would you do it לשם פסח leshem
pesach do you invalidate it. On after the 14th it's automatically a
שלמים. shlamim. If I took a normal קרבן korban that I made
a שלמים shlamim and I שחט shachted it on חול המועד Chol
HaMoed לשם פסח, leshem pesach, what would be its status? It would
be a שלמים שלא לשמו shlamim shelo lishmo which would be כשר.
kasher. Right? And you would fulfill... Right, but it would be כשר.
kasher. Okay, so why does the משנה Mishnah say when I שחט
shachat this פסח Pesach on the חול המועד Chol HaMoed לשם פסח
leshem pesach it's פסול? pasul. I mean it's לשם פסח leshem pesach
it's פסול? If it's just a שלמים shlamim I שחט shachted לשם
פסח. leshem pesach. Okay, that's what תוספות Tosafot says the question is.
So תוספות Tosafot says the reason only reason it's פסול is if
its identity as a פסח Pesach still exists beneath the surface. And
that's what the גמרא's Gemara asking. That we is that is that
if it's after if it's after
the 14th, if you're שחט shachting it לשם פסח leshem pesach can
still turn it into a פסח? Pesach I get that now it's
a שלמים shlamim but you have to admit that there's still some
you know submerged status of a פסח Pesach there because a normal
שלמים לשם פסח shlamim leshem pesach would not be פסול. And that's
why the גמרא Gemara is and that's for that the גמרא Gemara
has to give this answer that it's a special case.
Oh, no, that this one has been designated as a... Right.
But according to תוספות Tosafot the חידוש chiddush is when we say
a פסח Pesach after during after the 14th automatically converts to a
שלמים, shlamim, the question is, is there enough of a substratum of
פסח Pesach, there that if you did it לשם פסח leshem pesach
you could reawaken it? And that's the question תוספות Tosafot says the
גמרא's Gemara asking. Yes.
So there's there's I can see two cases. One is I declare
I say I point to my animal and say this is a
פסח, Pesach yeah, but I end up bringing a different animal as
my פסח. Pesach Now I've got this animal that's in there as
a פסח. Someone else could bring it on פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
Yeah, probably because you could be מושך ונמנה מידיהם. moshech venimne miyadeihem.
That's an interesting question. Why does it have to be the בעלים
are טמא? tamei? Why can't it be... I guess that כל זמן...
kol zman... That the בעלים have not- nobody else has- has by,
you know, has taken it over, it would still be defined by
the בעלים. Right? But in so- that right. Right. I could give
it to
someone who is טמא מת. tamei met.
Right, right, right. You're correct about that. Okay, all right.
So I was sort of thinking about the קרבן korban during פסח
the same way that we think about חמץ, like a חוזר ונעור?
chozeir vene'or? Right?
Because it can- Right, but he says that's the גמרא's Gemara question,
exactly. Okay. But that's really interesting.
Yeah. That they're treating the קרבן korban like dormant חמץ. That is
a way of thinking about it. Okay, fine. Let's take a look.
Okay. All right. So the גמרא Gemara. now gets to the next
משנה. Mishnah. Now we talk about the bringing of it.
So it's really a nice shift from these abstract questions of שלא
לשמו to a prohibition of שחיטת shechitat other קרבנות korbanot, to the
bringing of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Right? Now we're getting much
more concrete. הפסח נשחט בשלוש כיתות. HaPesach nishchat beshalosh kitot. The פסח
is slaughtered with three groups of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. Right? Everybody
comes in, they're three- it's a rotation, right? Three different groups come
into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash during the fourteenth, each group bringing,
you know, bringing their קרבנות. korbanot שנאמר ושחטו אותו כל קהל עדת
ישראל בין הערביים. Shene'emar veshachatu oto kol kehal adat Yisrael bein ha'arbayim.
So those three words, the congregation of the community of Israel, קהל
kehal and עדה edah and ישראל, Yisrael, each means that we're going
to do it as three separate groups. נכנסה כת ראשונה. Nichnesah kat
rishonah. The first group comes in. נתמלאה העזרה. Nitmal'ah ha'azarah. And
the עזרה azarah is filled with the Jews bringing their קרבן korban
פסח. נעלו דלתות העזרה. Na'alu daltot ha'azarah.
They were sealed, they were locked. Meaning okay, that's enough, we're full.
Everybody else has to wait till the next round. You know, it's
sort of like when you're at the amusement park, you know, and
you're standing in line and they click, click, click, okay, okay, that's
it, now everybody else will go for the next ride. All right.
So they lock the עזרה. azarah. תקעו והריעו ותקעו. Taku veheri'u vetaku.
So
they- they do a תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, which is
interesting, when they're bringing the קרבן Korban פסח. הכהנים עומדים שורות שורות.
Hakohanim omdim shurot shurot. The כהנים kohanim
are standing in rows. ובידיהם בזיכי כסף ובזיכי זהב. Uveyadeihem bezichei chesef
uvezichei zahav. And they have in their hands, you know, dishes- it's
got to be a better word, but anyway, bowls of silver and
bowls of gold. שורה שכולה כסף כסף שורה שכולה זהב זהב. Shurah
shekulah chesef chesef, shurah shekulah zahav zahav. If a row, a row
that's silver is all silver, a row that's gold is all gold.
ולא היו מעורבים. Velo hayu me'uravim. And they would- they would not
be mixed, the gold and the silver, the rows with one another.
ולא היו לבזיכים שוליים. Velo hayu labezichim shulayim. And these bowls would
not have a base. They would be like come to a point
at the bottom. You couldn't put it down. Why? שמא יניחום ויקרש
הדם. Shema yanichum veyikaresh hadam.
Because if they put it down, they'll forget about it and the
blood will congeal and then you can't do the זריקת הדם. zrikat
hadam. So you have to make sure you keep on holding it,
you never put it down until you are זורק zorek it. It
gets everything moving.
Was that true for all the קרבנות korbanot during the year or
just this particular?
No, I don't know.
I don't think so. I think קרישה krishah is an issue all
the time.
Right, but you don't have a million קרבנות and, you know, things
are a little bit slower. So you could- maybe since it's slower,
it's more likely you'll forget, you'll put it down, but you're not
as busy and distracted. Whereas here, right, you've got to make sure
that each one gets done. I don't think this was- right, exactly.
So here you have, right, here's your בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Okay. Here's your עזרת ישראל, ezrat Yisrael, which is only by the
way eleven אמות amot
wide and 135 אמות amot long. We'll talk about that. Okay.
Here- right, here's your מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay. So
you're- all- everybody's standing here. The כהנים kohanim are standing like this,
right? And these are the rows. So what happens is, is somebody
here, here's his קרבן, korban שחט, shachat, right? They catch the blood
and they do a, what's it called? A Chinese water thing? What
you- you know what that's called? Chinese water carry? Chinese- Chinese fire
drill? Fire drill, right. So, so this is all gold, let's say,
this is all silver. That's what it means, like they wouldn't be
mixed. This row would be all gold, this row would be all
silver. They wouldn't have them mixed in a row. This guy catches
it, he passes the bowl to him, to him, to him, to
him, and he throws it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And then when
he's done, it gets passed back, you know, this way. So you're
constantly moving one bowl and passing back the next and doing a
whole like conveyor belt to do it in a very efficient way.
Or was the שחיטה shechitah, was done in the בית המטבחיים? Beit
HaMitbachayim?
No, the שחיטה could be anywhere, it was not- it did not
require צפון. tzafon. So the בית המטבחיים Beit HaMitbachayim was for the
flay, we'll talk about that. The שחיטה was done- was done anywhere.
Okay. What comes into the שחיטה?
We're
going to talk about that. שחט ישראל וקיבל הכהן.
Shachat Yisrael
vekibel hakohein. So we've been saying normally the כהן- kohein normally the
כהן kohein שחט, shachat, but here it says a ישראל Yisrael שחט.
shachat. Now the גמרא Gemara. will say it means a ישראל Yisrael
is allowed to שחט, shachat, but there's actually a תוספתא Tosefta that-
that תוספות Tosafot quotes. If you look at the first תוספות, Tosafot,
קראו את ההלל, Karu et haHallel, it says פירש לויים, peireish Leviyim,
the לויים Leviyim read ההלל. haHallel. We're about to read that. דתניא
בתוספתא, Detanya beTosefta, ישראל שוחטים את פסחיהם ולויים קוראים את ההלל. Yisrael
shochtim et pischeihem uLeviyim korim et haHallel. הלל Hallel. *Hallel*. So and
that's actually quite nice because the תורה *Torah* says ושחטו אתו כל
קהל עדת ישראל Kahal Adat Yisrael. בין הערבים *ve'shachtu oto kol kehal
adat yisrael bein ha'arbayim*, right? That's where it really emphasizes that the
ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* is שוחט *shechting* the פסח *Pesach*. So even though
normally it's true that the owner or anybody could שוחט *shecht* a
קרבן korban *korban*, here although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
say לאו דוקא *lav davka* it just means that ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*
is allowed to, it sounds from the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* and the
תוספתא Tosefta, *Tosefta* that דוקא *davka* the owner is דוקא *davka* the
ישראל Yisrael? *Yisrael* would שוחט *shecht* their קרבנות *korbanot* and the כהנים
kohanim *Kohanim* would be מקבל *mekabel*, which by the way addresses some
of the issues that were bothering people before. If you have a
bad מחשבה *machshavah*, it's not fair, the כהן kohen *Kohen* has a
bad מחשבה *machshavah*, it hurts the owners. That's always a problem in
קדשים *kodshim*, but at least here it might be talking about the
owner who's שוחט *shechting* it is the one having the bad כוונה
*kavannah*.
Or if they had the right knife?
Yeah, that's a very, very good question. I don't know. And even
if it says that the ישראל Yisrael. *Yisrael* is שוחט *shechting*, it
doesn't have to mean that the owners are שוחט *shechting*. It might
just mean that they, you know, that they got all the שוחטים
shochtim *shochtim* in the neighborhood to come and to help with the
שחיטה *shechitah*. So, but you have the ישראל *Yisrael* is doing the
שחיטה *shechitah*, וקבל הכהן *ve'kibel ha-Kohen*, the כהן kohen? *Kohen* catches the
blood, נתנו לחברו *nosno l'chavero*, he gives it to his friend, the
guy behind him in the line, וחברו לחברו *ve'chavero l'chavero* and so
on, that one to the one behind him, ומקבל את המלא *u-m'kabel
et hamale*, you fetch from the guy in front of you, you
get the full thing of blood, ומחזיר את הריקן *u-machazir et hareikan*,
as you're getting the full one, you're giving him back the empty
one, right? Because if there are ten people in the line, then
there are ten dishes, okay, right? And it's constantly, you know, or
there are twenty dishes, I guess, are there twenty or are there
ten? No, I guess there are ten. How would it work? I
think there are ten. But anyway, you have to figure it out.
But you're constantly taking one and giving back the next. You're not
waiting till that one finishes and comes back around again, right? You're
constantly taking one and giving back the next and it's...
Did they hold it with two hands or...?
Yeah, you'd have to do it with, with two hands, it's
too normally, with two hands, right, you'd pass...
Right, you do it with two hands. No, but the עבודה avodah
*avodah*, the taking has to be with the right because the עבודה
avodah *avodah* is בימין *bi-yamin*, but the handing back is not an
עבודה avodah *avodah*, so that would be בשמאל *bi-smol*. I think there
would have to be twenty dishes if there were ten כהנים Kohanim
*Kohanim*, right? Because each one has one going this way and one
going back.
Anyway, let's just stick with the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*.
So that would be in one row it would be all of
one...? No, no, no, one row would be all the dishes being
used in one row would be silver, all the dishes in another
would be gold.
Did it matter if one was better than the other?
So yeah, no, well, I mean, one is a little nicer, but
it's an interesting question why they didn't do it all gold. I
imagine it looks more attractive, you know, when you have some alternating
going on.
I have a very annoying... yes, I can ask it now. If
it were raining,
they did it anyway, right?
In other words,
it could have been pouring.
Exactly. It's an interesting question, but yes. Okay, usually not a problem
in ישראל *Israel*. הכהן הקרוב אצל המזבח זורקו זריקה אחת כנגד היסוד
*ha-Kohen hakarov etzel ha-mizbeach zorko zrika achas keneged ha-yesod*. The כהן kohen
*Kohen* near the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeach* throws one זריקה *zrika*, one throwing
on the wall opposite the base. Now isn't everything opposite the base?
So the answer is no, everything is not opposite the base because,
one minute,
right, so because the base, the base of the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*
only went like this, okay? On the south and on the east,
there was actually no, I mean, obviously there was a base, but
there wasn't a protruding base, okay? It didn't protrude from the bottom.
The protrusion at the base only was in the west and the
north in these corners. So the זריקה *zrika*, by the way, of
like a of a normal קרבן korban. *korban* would be on these
two corners because then it would be able to hit all four
directions, but it would be כנגד היסוד *keneged ha-yesod*, you would hit
the wall, right? You're hitting the wall and here is your protruding
base, I don't know, let's look at it anyway, you throw it
on the wall, the blood splatters like this and then it runs
down to the base. Okay?
That's how it's like a...
Like a funnel. So that's your normal קרבן *korban* that's not a
חטאת *chatas*. You throw it at those corners, it hits and there's
a base on both sides there and it runs down. שתים שהן
ארבע *shtayim shehen arba*, two which are four, because it there are
four your sides that are included. The קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* does
not require those two corners, but it has to be on one
of the sides that has a base. It cannot be thrown against
one of these walls. It has to be thrown against a wall
that it can run to the base. Okay? But they're not by
the base, they're not by the base. It can't, it cannot be
these walls. Right?
Not these walls, but anywhere along these walls it
can be, and then it'll hit, run to the base.
So where are they throwing the blood? Anywhere against these walls. The
base on the diagram's a little off.
It's not
on the base, you throw it on the wall and it runs
down to the base.
So where... but they're not... the way the diagram is... Oh, the
way the diagram is. Oh, that's a very... that's an excellent point!
I wasn't thinking about that. You'd have to continue, that's a good
point, I wasn't thinking about that. You'd have to continue and go,
and go, this really shows you why
you need...
That would be, that would
be a real problem, you're right.
You'd have to, you couldn't even go straight.
Okay, and how much room there is between the...
exactly. No, there is some, but not much. Okay, so it's a
very good point. All right, so, יצאה
כת ראשונה, the first group went out.
נכנסה כת שנייה, nichnesa kat sheniya, the second group came in. יצאה
שנייה נכנסה שלישית, Yatza sheniya nichnesa shlishit, second went out, third came
in. כמעשה ראשונה כך מעשה שנייה והשלישית, ke-ma'aseh rishona kach ma'aseh sheniya
ve-hashlishit, whatever you did with the first group, the same procedure second,
and same with second and third. קראו את ההלל. karu et ha-Hallel.
Now, what they also did, I mean, it's a little funny to
double back to say this, while they're שוחטים shochtim, the קרבן פסח,
they're reading the הלל. Hallel, And as we saw in תוספות Tosafot
quoting the תוספתא, Tosefta the לויים Levi'im are reading the הלל, Hallel
which is okay.
אם גמרו, im gamru, if they finished the הלל Hallel and that
group was still bringing their קרבנות, because there's a lot of קרבנות
to bring, שנו, shanu, they did, they said the הלל Hallel a
second time. ואם שנו, ve-im shanu, and if they did it a
second time and they still are not done bringing the קרבנות, שלשלו,
shilshilu, they did it a third time. אף על פי שלא שלשלו
מימיהם, af al pi she-lo shilshilu mi-yemeihem, but they never had to
get to a third time, which is okay. Meaning that there was
never so many קרבנות in any one group that they had to
do it three times. By the way, according to some, the reason
we say הלל Hallel on פסח night in שול shul at night,
those who have that מנהג—we minhag never say הלל Hallel at night—is
a זכר zecher for the הלל Hallel that was said on ערב
פסח when they brought their קרבן פסח. Okay, so that's the reading
of the הלל Hallel here. One minute. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, מימיהם של כת שלישית, mi-yemeihem shel
kat shlishit, not only did in the first groups they never get
around to doing it three times, but for the, you know, you
know, in history, the third group, לא הגיעו לאהבתי כי ישמע ה',
lo higiu le-Ahavti ki yishma Hashem,
they never got to אהבתי כי ישמע ה'—that Ahavti ki yishma Hashem
פסוק in הלל—even Hallel the first time because it was so small.
So the third group, he says, never even finished הלל Hallel. once.
So this is a little bit, you know, a little disappointing because
it sounds like how many people could there have been, you know,
that that you can't even get to- now who knows how long
it takes to say הלל. Hallel I was recently at a wedding
that, you know, and they said one פסוק, it took twenty minutes,
you know, when they were- you know, they had some חזן chazan
there for the procession and they were saying something like- so depending
on the חזנות, chazzanut, you know, הלל Hallel. could take an hour
I imagine. Yeah, I've been to some hour-long הלל. Hallel. So I
don't know if this is a good measure of how few the
people were or how long it took the לויים Levi'im to say
the הלל.
Hallel Strange, as this is a פלא pele here in the Hebrew
Institute.
Yeah, right. Okay, let's read a little more. Okay, so we gotta
get a little further.
Okay, so okay. מועטין. mu'atin. כמעשהו בחול כך מעשהו בשבת, ke-ma'aseihu be-chol
kach ma'aseihu be-Shabbat, like they would do during the weekday they do
on שבת, Shabbat, אלא—except ella on שבת Shabbat you can't roast the
פסח until the night—אלא שהכהנים מדיחין את העזרה שלא ברצון חכמים. ella
she-ha-kohanim madichin et ha-azarah she-lo birtson chachamim. But what the- what the
כהנים kohanim would do, they would do it during the week, is
there'd be so much blood on the floor of the עזרה, azarah,
it's pretty hard to work with all that blood running on the
floor. So they would stop up—they had like a water flowing through,
and when they would stop it up like a dam, it would
overflow and it would rinse the עזרה, azarah, and then you- you
know and then it would be like in Israel, like this, you
know, the squeegee, you know where you do it into a hole,
you know, the sponge and you- and you sponge it into the
hole and it goes down. So they would do that on שבת
Shabbat like they would do in the weekday, and the חכמים chachamim
did not like that they were doing this on שבת. Shabbat. Okay,
we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara
רבי יהודה אומר, now, back to the procedure. רבי יהודה said, כוס
היה ממלא מדם התערובת וזרקו זריקה אחת על גבי
המזבח. kos haya memale mi-dam ha-ta'aroveit ve-zarko zrika achat al gabei mizbe'ach.
רבי יהודה said at the end of the process, maybe at the
end of each group, you would take- you would of the blood
that was on the floor since we're talking about that, you scoop
up some of the blood on the floor and you throw it
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, Why? Because he would be concerned that some
blood spilled and that- and the blood of some קרבן may have
never got to the מזבח. mizbe’ach? Maybe all the blood of a
קרבן spilled on the floor. So assuming that all the bloods mixed
equally, which is an interesting assumption, he's going to say if you
take some of the blood on the floor and you throw it,
then any blood of any קרבן will have gotten to the מזבח.
mizbe’ach? Now that assumes a couple of things which we'll discuss in
the גמרא. Gemara Yes, Charlie. Two questions. Wait, ולא הודו לו חכמים,
ve-lo hodu lo chachamim, but the חכמים chachamim did not agree with
this. Yes.
If we're going to recite הלל זכר zecher for קרבן פסח, shouldn't
we be doing it בין הערביים be-vein ha-arbayim rather than...
Yeah, okay. Yeah.
And second, what is wrong with rinsing the temple with some fine?
We'll get to it. Okay. כיצד תולין ומפשיטין. keitzad tolin u-mafshitin. How
would you suspend and flay the קרבן פסח? You had to flay
it to get out the אימורים, emurim, so you were allowed to
flay it to get out right the innards and the fats to
burn so you were allowed to flay it even on שבת. Shabbat.
It was not just to prepare the meat, it was to prepare
it was to do the עבודה of the קרבן to get out
the אימורים. emurim. So how would you- how would you flay... How
they used to stand and flay the קרבן פסח. You had to
flay it to get out the אימורים, emurim, so you were allowed
to flay it to get out, right, the innards and the fat
to burn, so you were allowed to flay it even on שבת.
Shabbat. It was not just to prepare the meat, it was to
prepare, it was to do the עבודה of the קרבן to get
out the אימורים. emurim. So how would you flay, how would you
suspend it and flay it? אונקליות של ברזל unkelyot shel barzel iron
hooks היו קבועים בכתלים hayu kevuim biktalim they had in the walls
ובעמודים uva'amudim or on posts, and this דף daf is the בית
המטבחיים Beit HaMitbachayim where they had these posts with iron hooks שבהן
תולין ומפשיטין shebahen tolin u'mafshitin they would hang the carcass on them
and flay it. כל מי שאין לו מקום לתלות ולהפשיט, kol mi
she'ein lo makom litlot ul'hafshit,
anybody who did not have a place, right, there were so many,
let's say you didn't have all the hooks were in use, so
what would they do? מקלות דקים וחלקים היו שם maklot dakkim ve'chalakim
hayu sham they would have thin and smooth poles there in the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they would hand it out. Oh wait,
all the hooks are being used? Here, take this pole. And what
would you do with this pole? So מניח על כתפו ועל כתף
חבירו meniach al ktefo ve'al ktef chaveiro
you'd put it on your shoulder and your friend's shoulder, you would
be the post, you know, and you'd hold the pole up, ותולה
ומפשיט ve'toleh u'mafshat
and you suspend it from there. I hope that these posts, that
these poles had hooks also, but okay, and you would suspend it
on this pole that you're holding up and you would flay it.
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, Rabbi Eliezer says, י"ד שחל להיות
בשבת yud dalet she'chal lihyot b'Shabbat top of the עמוד ב' amud
bet if we were talking about that the fourteenth is on שבת,
Shabbat, then when you said it's just like the weekday, here's how
it's different. It's not just like the weekday. מניח ידו על כתף
חבירו ויד חבירו על כתפו meniach yado al ktef chaveiro ve'yad chaveiro
al ktefo
you don't even use a pole, you use your arms. You put
your arm on his shoulder, his arm on your shoulder, that's the
pole, ותולה ומפשיט ve'toleh u'mafshat
and you suspend and you flay it because, very bizarre, what's the
big deal about using a pole? It's going to turn out to
be like some type of a מוקצה muktzah concern, but there's all
of this עבודה being done, we're שוחטים, flaying, burning, and we have
to worry that the poles are מוקצה. muktzah. So anyway, we'll talk
about that when we get to it. The other thing though I
don't really get is, you know, again, you got your arms, but
what's it sticking on? Where's the hook? Right? I still don't understand
how it's being held up with just your arms. Do you like
what? Like you like flap it over?
I'm not, it's not going to work. It's not going to work.
I don't understand
it.
Talking about a
heavy animal. I know. Yeah, I don't get it. Okay. Okay, קרעו
kar'o
they tore it meaning they
they cut it, you know, lengthwise. הוציא את אימוריו hotzi et emurav
they took out the innards, you know, the intestines and the fats,
נתנו במגיס netano b'magis they put it in a plate, הקטירו על
גבי מזבח hiktiro al gabbe hamizbeach and they burnt it on the
altar. יצתה כת ראשונה וישבה לה בהר הבית. yatz'ta kat rishonah ve'yashvah
lo b'Har HaBayit. Now, this is specifically on שבת. Shabbat. If it's
a weekday, the first group goes out then they go home, but
if it's שבת, Shabbat, you can't carry. So what are you going
to do? So thankfully,
all of הר הבית Har HaBayit was surrounded by a wall. The
כותל kotel is the wall of הר הבית, Har HaBayit, right? It
is not the wall of the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so all of
הר הבית Har HaBayit was surrounded by a wall, so the first
group went out and they sat on הר הבית. Har HaBayit.
That explains why the כותל kotel is in
the west from where,
right, the west, correct.
Because if you look at this, right, here's why I have this
picture, this is the כותל kotel around the הר הבית, Har HaBayit,
this is the Temple, okay, but this, which side is the west?
This is the west, right, and which side is the south? This.
These are the two walls that we have now in Israel, right?
So the west is the west wall, no, the north,
I'm sorry.
Oh, so it's the south, though, is that other those they can
talk from? So that is further away.
Okay, but at least the western wall is right up against, there's
almost no space between that and the קודש הקדשים, Kodesh HaKodashim, but
from other places there was a much bigger distance.
Well now anyway, from this southern wall is a big cliff.
Right,
so that's exactly this, this is the southern part, exactly that.
Well, they could, at different places I'm sure were able. Anyway, so
they left and they sat somewhere on הר הבית Har HaBayit which
was surrounded by a wall, and that's where they were. One minute.
Okay, we I don't think let's hold the questions because we got
a lot to talk. I had I had to look this up.
Oh, how much does a ram weigh? Average is ten pounds for
a newborn.
Ten pounds for newborn, but a lot of these lambs
would be newborns, they're just spring.
Uh-huh, okay, but how much once it's a year old? That you
don't know. All right, we'll get the range. Anyway,
והראשונה יצאה הר הבית, ve'harishonah yatz'ta Har HaBayit, שניה בחיל והשלישית במקומה
עומדת. shniyah b'cheil ve'hashlishit bimkomah omedet. The second one waited in the
חיל. cheil. What was the חיל? cheil? The חיל cheil
was this little area, right,
a minute, right, this is called, right, this here, this little exterior
wall here, right,
is called is called the סורג. soreg. This little gap between the
סורג soreg and where things begin is called the חיל. cheil. So
they spent in that little gap. I guess they would have to
spread out to really, if there were a lot of people. So
that's where they would wait. I don't know why they had to
maintain the idea of a different group. Just go out and wait
on הר הבית. Har HaBayit. There's a lot more room. Yeah, yeah,
I mean women could go all in this space. I mean women
could even go in the עזרה Azara sometimes too. But I don't
understand. This is such a thin space. I don't understand why they
had to wait here. Who needs to maintain the distinctive nature of
the groups after you're done?
Okay. They couldn't go home with it.
I know, but wait on הר הבית Har HaBayit with the first
group.
For the whole rest of the afternoon.
Yeah, they had to wait until nightfall. But I just don't get
why they didn't wait on הר הבית Har HaBayit with the rest
of them.
It would have taken up all this space.
I guess, no, you're right, part of it is a precipitous drop,
so you really can't spend in all the space. But it's hard
for me to imagine that there was no space here and you
had to squeeze into this little gap.
Yeah, and the commentaries to מסכת תמיד Masechet Tamid actually have a
different layout that has much greater space between the עזרת נשים Ezrat
Nashim and the היכל. Heichal.
All right, okay, so maybe there is a greater gap. I mean,
there are different opinions. Okay, so maybe there is a greater gap
there. Okay, all right. So anyway, moving on. שלישית במקומה עומדת. Shlishit
B'makoma Omedet. The third group
stayed in the עזרה. Azara. חשכה, Chashecha,
then it became dark. Finally, יצאו וצלו את פסחם. Yatzu V'tzalu Et
Pischan. They could go home and roast their קרבן פסח. Now, this
is on Friday, this is when it's on שבת. Shabbat. Oh, that's
all.
Did they have to eat?
Well, wherever they were staying, wherever they were staying in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Right, they would go to where they're staying in ירושלים Yerushalayim and
roast their קרבן פסח. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רבי יצחק אין הפסח נשחט אלא בג' כיתות של שלושים שלושים בני
אדם. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Ein HaPesach Nishchat Ela B'gimel Kitot Shelo Shlohim
Shlohim Bnei Adam. Not only do we need three groups, each group
has to have thirty people. מאי טעמא? Why? קהל עדת ישראל. Kahal
Adat Yisrael, Because it says קהל עדת ישראל, those three terms, each
one we assume means a group of ten. So מסתפקא ליה. Mistafka
Lei. אי בבת אחת. I B'vat Achat. Does it mean all three
groups at once, so you have to have thirty at any one
time? אי בזה אחר זה. I B'zeh Achar Zeh. Or do you
have to have three separate groups, which is what the משנה Mishna
says? So he says, to cover our bases, הלכך בעינן ג' כיתות
של שלושים שלושים בני אדם. Hilkach Ba'inan Shalosh Kitot Shelo Shlohim Shlohim
Bnei Adam. Therefore, we do three groups of thirty to cover our
bases. Maybe the תורה means thirty, maybe it means three groups of
ten. דאי בבת אחת היכא. De'i B'vat Achat Heika. If it meant
thirty at one time, we've got it. דאי בזה אחר זה היכא.
De'i B'zeh Achar Zeh Heika. And if it meant three separate times,
we've got it. הלכך, Hilkach, the גמרא Gemara says, הלכך, Hilkach, you
know what? Therefore, you really don't need ninety. Three times thirty is
ninety. חמשים נמי סגי. Chamishim Nami Sagi. You can really get away
with fifty. How do you get away with fifty? דעייל תלתין ועבדי.
De'ayeil Tlatzin V'avdi. You get thirty in the first group. They bring
the קרבן פסח. So that covers our bases if the תורה means
thirty at one time.
עיילו עשרה ונפקו עשרה. Ayeilu Asara V'nafku Asara. Ten go out, twenty
stay around. This is sort of like what we do when by
התרת נדרים Hatarat Nedarim on ערב ראש השנה. Erev Rosh Hashanah. Right,
two have to stay and wait even though they're done. But one
group of ten goes out and a new group of ten comes
in. So now you have a second group at a second time.
But if you needed thirty at one time,
that new group of ten has these twenty old guys that are
helping make their presence as a part of a group of
thirty. Okay. דנפקו ועיילו עשרה ונפקו עשרה. De'nafku V'ayeilu Asara V'nafku Asara.
So then, the final group of ten comes in and the one
group of ten goes out. So you can get by with fifty.
Okay, so this is a variation on the משנה that only mentioned
three separate groups. He speaks about the idea of having thirty at
any given time. נכנסה כת ראשונה. Niknesa Kat Rishona. The first group
goes in. איתמר. Itmar. And then says they lock the עזרה. Azara.
אביי אמר
ננעלו. Abaye Amar Ninalu. The doors lock by themselves. תנן. Tnan. רבא
אמר נועלין. Rava Amar Noalin. We lock the doors. תנן. Tnan. מאי
בינייהו? Mai Beiniyhu? What do they disagree about? איכא בינייהו למסמך אניסא.
Ika Beiniyhu Lismach A'nisa. To rely on a miracle. אביי Abaye assumes
that a miracle happens and the doors just locked on their own
accord. אביי אמר ננעלו תנן. Abaye Amar Ninalu Tnan. כמה דעייל מעייל.
Kama D'ayeil Meiyeil.
As much as as long as people could get in, they would
go in. דסמכינן אניסא. D'samchinan A'nisa. And we rely on the miracle
that, you know how we'll know that we have enough? When the
doors lock by themselves. And we assume that that miracle will occur.
רבא אמר נועלין תנן. Rava Amar Noalin Tnan. I'm sorry, we monitor
how many people are going in and we lock the doors. We
don't wait for them to lock themselves. ולא סמכינן אניסא. V'lo Samchinan
A'nisa. דהא תנן. Deha Tnan.
Now we have a משנה where we're going to apply this same
debate. אמר רבי יהודה חס ושלום שעקביא בן מהללאל נתנדה. Amar Rabbi
Yehuda Chas V'shalom She'akvya Ben Mahalalel Nitnade.
Okay, so there's a story that עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya Ben Mahalalel
said something, it's very interesting, about a סוטה. Sota. The גמרא Gemara
discusses whether certain women, like a freed slave, would go through the
סוטה Sota process. And עקביא Akavya said no. And they said, ah,
don't we know that שמעיה ואבטליון, Shmaya V'avtalyon, you know, did this
with a freed slave woman, you know, went through the whole process
of the סוטה? Sota? And he said, nah, that was just a
fake. Meaning they made it look like they were making her drink
the water, but it was a placebo, it was something else. So
then the גמרא Gemara doesn't like that at all to think that
they would do that and it would be a fake. And it
says they put him in חרם, Cherem, they put him in נידוי.
Niduy. So then the response of רבי יהודה is, חס ושלום שעקביא
בן מהללאל נתנדה. Chas V'shalom She'akvya Ben Mahalalel Nitnade. God forbid that
עקביא בן מהללאל Akavya Ben Mahalalel should ever be put in נידוי.
Niduy. שאין עזרה ננעלת על כל אדם בישראל. She'ein Azara Nin'elet Al
Kol Adam B'yisrael.
And the doors of the עזרה Azarah were sealed, referring to this,
when you had it packed because it was ערב פסח and the
doors were sealed, so you had everybody together, at that moment you
will never find in all of those people anybody that equals בחכמה
וביראת חטא כאכביא בן מהללאל, b'chochmah u'v'yirat cheit k'Akavia ben Mahalalel, anybody
that equals in wisdom or in fear of sin as Akavia ben
Mahalalel. So it's a way of saying nobody in the entire כל
ישראל, Klal Yisrael, but it uses this image of when the doors
of the עזרה Azarah were locked on ערב פסח. So אביי מתרץ
לטעמיה רבא מתרץ לטעמיה, Abayei metareitz l'taameih Rava metareitz l'taameih, each one
explains based on their understanding. אביי מתרץ לטעמיה אין בעזרה בשעה שננעלה
על כל אדם בישראל כחכם וירא חטא כאכביא בן מהללאל. Abayei metareitz
l'taameih ein ba'azarah b'sha'ah she-nin'alah al kol adam b'Yisrael k'chacham v'yarei cheit
k'Akavia ben Mahalalel. When the עזרה Azarah locked itself, right, passive like,
locked itself, nobody was there as wise and as fearful of sin
as Akavia ben Mahalalel. רבא מתרץ לטעמיה אין בעזרה בשעה שנועלים אותה,
Rava metareitz l'taameih ein ba'azarah b'sha'ah she-no'alim otah, when we lock the
עזרה Azarah you'll not find in there על כל ישראל בחכמה וביראת
חטא כאכביא בן מהללאל. al kol Yisrael b'chochmah u'v'yirat cheit k'Akavia ben
Mahalalel. And the מסורה Masora is not מכריע machriya one way or
the other. Right, it's very funny how the גמרא Gemara brings that
in. It just says this idea of עזרה ננעלה azarah nin'ela is
a phrase that comes up in this story four times. I know.
Alright, it's funny how some גמראס Gemoras are like
are so dense and some go very quickly. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
a rabbi starts. מעולם לא נתמעך אדם בעזרה, me'olam lo nitma'eich adam
ba'azarah, it was so crowded, you know, you'd think people would get
crushed, but nobody was ever crushed חוץ מפסח אחד, chutz mi-Pesach echad,
but actually it did happen once, שהיה בימי הלל, she-hayah bi-ymei Hillel,
in the time of Hillel, שנתמעך בו זקן אחד, she-nitma'eich bo zaken
echad, a certain elderly person was crushed, והיו קוראין אותו פסח מעוכין,
v'hayu korin oto Pesach Me'uchin, and they called it the crushed Pesach,
the Pesach of crushing to remember this tragedy. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
now we have another story that maybe is also maybe from a
similar tradition of this פסח מעוכין, Pesach Me'uchin, we'll see.
It's also funny to say it was a miracle, it never happened
except once.
Well, the fact that we say it happened once gives greater substantiation
to the claim that it never happened any other time. תנו רבנן
פעם אחת ביקש אגריפס המלך ליתן עיניו באוכלוסי ישראל. Tanu Rabbanan pa'am
achat bikkeish Agrippas ha-Melech litein einav b'uchlusei Yisrael. One time Agrippas the
king, right,
one of the kings at the end of the period of בית
שני, Bayit Sheni, wanted to get, you know, for pride get a
sense of the vast numbers of the Jewish people that he was
ruling over. אמר ליה לכהן גדול, Amar leih l'kohein gadol, he said
to the כהן גדול, Kohein Gadol, תן עיניך בפסחים, tein einecha b'Psachim,
count look at the Psachim, count how many Psachim they're bringing and
then we'll do a it's a rough way to do a consensus,
not that one פסח equals one person, we'll see roughly one פסח
equals ten people. Okay, so it'll be a rough
consensus, consensus of not everybody, maybe the men, we'll see about whether
the women also brought, but anyway that'll be a rough consensus.
נטלו כוליא מכל אחד, Natlu kulyah mi-kol echad, he took a kidney
from each פסח, collected the kidneys and then they counted the kidneys.
ונמצאו שם, V'nimtze'u sham, as a way of like, you know, just
marking it and keeping track, שישים ריבוא זוגי כליות. shishim ribo zugei
klyot. They found six hundred thousand pairs of kidneys, which means 1.2
million
פסחים. Psachim. כפליים כיוצאי מצרים, kiflayim k'yotzei Mitzrayim, double those that left
Egypt, this is clearly exaggerated, חוץ מטמא ושהיה בדרך רחוקה, chutz mi-tamei
u'she-hayah b'derech rechokah, and that doesn't even include the people that weren't
able to bring their
פסח because they were טמאי. tmei. ואין לך כל פסח ופסח שלא
נמנו עליו יותר מעשרה בני אדם, V'ein lecha kol Pesach u'Pesach she-lo
nimnu alav yoteir me-asarah b'nei adam, and there's no קורבן פסח korban
Pesach that had fewer than ten people. So basically it means how
many people were there? Twelve million! Okay, adult males, assuming males, we'll
talk about we'll talk about women later.
But that's 12 million people who eat it.
Right, right,
and that's only the people who are eating the okay fine, I
don't want to get into fine, we won't get into women and
men right now, that'll be a later discussion. Anyway, 12 million people.
I doubt that there were 12 million people in the world at
that time. Charlie probably knows world population.
The estimated population of the Roman Empire was about 50
million.
50? 5-0? About 50 million in the entire Roman Empire and about
the same number in China.
Okay fine, so there were a hundred million people in the entire
world.
Anyway, it was as high as 12 million in that little tiny
adjacent area.
Now okay so this is now by the way, now by the
way I do want to make a point about that about numbers
because this space which is the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, the thin
like sliver, you see it like in front of the מזבח, mizbe’ach...
it was 135 אמה amah long by 11 אמה amah wide which
is roughly
1400 square אמה, amah, right? 135 times 10, whatever, 1400 square אמה.
amah. If one person stands in a square אמה, amah, that's 1400
people. Even if it's crushed, so what are you gonna get, two
people in a square אמה? amah? Three people? Okay we're talking about
what, 3000 people, 5000 people? So at most that could fit three
groups would be about 15,000 people.
How
is everybody bringing their קורבן פסח? korban Pesach? I don't know. Besides
this story is obviously an exaggeration. I don't get how everybody bring
their קורבן פסח. korban Pesach. You know, certainly not that they're all
fitting in. Maybe there could be multiple פסחים Pesachs for each person
representing other people. But then,
I don't know.
It was a crowded קידוש. Kiddush.
I don't get how, I don't get how... No, but just thinking
about when the תורה says everybody is עולה לרגל, oleh l'regel, right?
How do you have the time to bring all those קרבנות פסח
Korban Pesachs if you really have everybody being עולה לרגל? oleh l'regel?
Anyway, it ends by saying, let's just end this, ויקראו אותו פסח
מעובין. Vayikre’u oto Pesach me’uvin. So as opposed to before, מעוכין, me’uchin,
crushed, here it’s מעובין, me’uvin, a thick פסח because there were so
many people. So now the גמרא Gemara analyzes this question. נטל כוליא,
Natal kulya, he took a kidney? הכתיב הקטרה, Ha'ketiv haktarah, you have
to burn the kidney on the מזבח? mizbeach. All right, דהדר מקטרו
להו, Dehadar maktru lehu, fine. After they did the count, they burned
them. והכתיב והקטירה, Ve’haktiv ve’haktirah, you should burn it? שלא יערב, She'lo
ye'arev, singular, חלבו chelevo של זה בזה, shel zeh bazeh, that you
don't mix up one fat of one קרבן with another and here
you're going to do the kidneys of all the קרבנות at the
same time? דהדר מקטרו להו חדא חדא. Dehadar maktru lehu chada chada.
Fine, when you burn it, you do one at a time, one,
then one, you don't throw it all on. Okay, the גמרא Gemara
says, והתניא והקטירם, Ve’hatanya ve’haktiram, you should burn them? שכולן כאחת, She’kulan
k’achat, all of the innards, all of the fats of one קרבן
are together, so you can't do the kidney separate from the other
fat. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא תפיסה בעלמא, Ella tefisa b'alma,
he didn't really hold onto it, he just grabbed it, he held
it up, דשקיל מינייהו, de’shakil mineihu, right, and he took one of
them עד דיהיב ליה מידי אחרינא, ad de’yahiv leh midi achrina, and
then they put another marker, meaning, here you have somebody there that's
holding up the kidney so some other כהן kohen. who's keeping track
can make a mark, and then you put the kidney back with
the rest of the קרבן. Anyway, that is according to this story.
קצלי, Katzly, do you have a weight for us for a one-year-old
lamb? No.
Okay, but a
newborn lamb is eight to ten pounds.
I was going to like, they will generally be adult weight by
a year, but different times of sheep can be anywhere from thirty
pounds to one hundred fifty.
Okay, all right, let's do a little bit more. כהנים עומדים שורות
שורות. Kohanim omdim shurot shurot. So כהנים would be in their lines
and you wouldn't mix gold and silver. מאי טעמא? Why not? אילימא
דילמא משקלי דהבא ומייתי דכספא, Ilima dilma mashkli dehavah u'maiti d'chaspa,
because maybe what you'll do is you'll be giving back gold and
you'll be taking silver, so you'll be going down as it were,
because silver is less valuable than gold and that won't be appropriate,
you know, you're giving away the gold and taking the silver when
you're in this assembly line. בהכי נמי? Be’hachi nami? דילמא שקיל בר
מאתן ומייתי בר מאה? Dilma shakil bar matan u’maiti bar me’ah?
You could be handing back one that's worth two hundred זוז zuz
and taking one, or שקל, shekel, and taking one that's worth only
one hundred, so it's always possible what you're taking is worth less
than the empty one that you're giving back. אלא דהכי שפיר טפי.
Ella de’hachi shapir tefei. You know why you don't mix gold and
silver? It looks nicer that way. You have one row of all
gold, one row of all silver, it's more aesthetically pleasing. Okay, ולא
היו לבזיכין שוליים. Ve’lo hayu l’vazichin shulayim. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Oh,
this actually, כל הבזיכין. Kol habazichin. Oh, I,
דב, Dov, this answers your question. This answers your question, דב, Dov,
I had forgotten this when you asked your question. כל הבזיכין שבמקדש
לא היו להם שוליים. Kol habazichin she’be’Mikdash lo hayu lahem shulayim.
There's your answer. All of the bowls did not have a base,
because you never wanted any of the blood of the things to
be put down and it'll congeal. חוץ מבזיכי
לבונה, Chutz m’vazichei levonah, the only exception they would have would be
the little sort of spoons that they would have for the frankincense
that they would put on the שולחן shulchan with the לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, של לחם הפנים, shel lechem hapanim, they would have to
lay it flat on the שולחן. shulchan. If it didn't have a
base, it would have to lean against something.
That spoon actually was on the מזבח? mizbeach.
It was on the שולחן, shulchan, on the שולחן. shulchan.
It wasn't a pan, it was a little amount and it was
on the שולחן. shulchan. So anyway, if you're leaving it on the
שולחן shulchan for the week, it has to be flat. And right,
because if not, שמא יניחום, shema yanichum, because if not you would
put it and you'd lean it against the bread and ויפרסו הלחם,
v’yipresu halechem, it would break the bread. The bread was very delicately
made. Okay, we'll do one more thing. שחט ישראל וקיבל הכהן. Shachat
Yisrael ve’kibel ha’Kohen. The ישראל slaughtered
and, as we said, the תוספתא makes it sound like דווקא davka
the ישראל would do the שחיטה, but that's not what the גמרא
says. לא סגיא דלאו ישראל? Lo sagya delav Yisrael? So, is
it not, it has to be a ישראל? What, it can't be
a כהן? kohen No, היא גופא קא משמע לן. Hi gufa ka
mashma lan. No, it's just telling us the הלכה, halacha, דשחיטה בזר
כשרה, deshchitah be’zar kesherah, that it's allowed to be with a ישראל.
וקיבל הכהן? Ve’kibel ha’Kohen?
Why does it say the כהן kohen captures the blood in the
vessel? קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, מקבלה ואילך מצוות כהונה, mikabalah
v’eilach mitzvat kehunah, to tell you that starting after the שחיטה, starting
in the קבלה, kabalah, that that has to be a כהן. נותנו
לחברו. Notno l’chavero.
He gives it to his friend and they did this whole like
Chinese water carrier, שמע מינה הולכה שלא ברגל הוי הולכה. Shma minah
holachah she’lo b’regel havei holachah.
Oh, we got a problem. You're getting it to the מזבח... Nobody
is moving. Nobody is actually taking a step. But one of the
עבודות avodos is the act of getting it to the מזבח. So
can you do an הולכה holacha without actually moving your legs? Does
that count as an הולכה? holacha? So the גמרא says הולכה holacha
without feet. Right.
Or transport without feet. Okay. Without walking. So the גמרא says דלמא
דהני פורתא, dilma dahani purta, maybe he took a little baby step.
Okay. So before you handed it to the guy behind you, or
maybe the כהן who, the last כהן who had it, maybe he
took a little baby step to get to the מזבח. ואלא מאי
קמשמע לן, V'ela mai kamashma lan, so what's it teaching us? הא
קמשמע לן ברוב עם הדרת מלך. Ha kamashma lan b'rov am hadrat
melech. We did it not, why are you making a point that
there was this whole procedure? There was this whole like assembly line.
Not to say that, not to say that what? Not to say
that you don't need to do an act of הולכה, holacha, but
to show you how many people they got involved in order so,
then it was to, in order to make it such a, you
know, such a beautiful event and such an honorable event. The more
people you get involved, even in the procedure of it and the
כהנים you get involved, the more beautiful that the event is. Okay,
we will end with this.
One correction, it's actually a bucket brigade.
Oh, bucket brigade! Thank you, that's what it's called. Okay, not Chinese
water... Okay, so what does that refer to, something else? There is
a Chinese water but that's when you actually are moving. The bucket
brigade is you're standing and you're just moving and they're just moving
the bucket. Okay, very important correction.
Fire drill is when you run around, you know, everyone gets out
of the car, runs around, and gets back in.
No, I thought that was clowns at the circus.